<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Career | Shaan Aucharagram</title>
    <link>/category/career/</link>
      <atom:link href="/category/career/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Career</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Shaan Aucharagram © 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/avatar.jpg</url>
      <title>Career</title>
      <link>/category/career/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Networking 101</title>
      <link>/post/networking-101/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/networking-101/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One skill that they don’t teach you at school and what I recently knew very little about, networking. How does one network? It is arguably one of the most sought out skills from the younger generation, who are savvier in terms of hard skills, subsequently neglecting the soft skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One word, for any young professionals regardless of where you live, regardless of where you are, networking is key to job-hunting. Regardless of how skilled you are within your particular profession, you may be the worlds best coder, the worlds best lawyer, however, if you have no-one to vouch for you, it makes the legitimacy of your claim less substantial. By networking, you have the chance to almost “cut-out” part of the application process where you need to ap[ly for jobs, by having a network of people available to you, the jobs will come to you rather than the other way round.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linkedin. What is that? Only the internets most used platform by job seekers. The trick is too not apply to jobs directly, but to reach out to others within the company. Directors, people within your field, someone that you can idolize too. Arrange a meeting in person, or if you live in an unreasonable destination for a meet-up in person, ask for a phone call or Zoom meeting. I promise you, people when they see you make a conscious effort to network, will go out of there way to meet up with you. I was surprised when I started networking via Linkedin, how many people I was able to reach, especially by living in London I have had the opportunity to meet some incredible individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next is specific networking events, this can be through Eventbrite or an alternative platform. Attend them, regardless of how you perceive them, the only way you can network is if there are new people to meet, right. So what better way to meet with like-minded people who also want to meet new people. Go up to people and make engaging conversations, don’t have one-sided conversations make sure both yourself and the other person you are talking to are both conversing. If you don’t live in a place feasible to attend networking events, I have one word for you, webinars. These are great ways to meet new people without having the facilities to meet in person and can expose you to multiple people throughout the globe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the key tips that I would recommend to any young person is to not pigeon-hole themselves in their own industry. What does that mean? Do not only network with people within the same job function as yourself. For example, I work within Data Science at Santander, pigeon-holing would mean only networking with people within technology, within the finance sector or/and within the same company. Whilst it is obviously beneficial to have these types of people in your network. Expand, network with people from different job families to different companies, you never know what the future may hold and having a broad network allows you to explore different opportunities within the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I struggled with a lot and I know a lot of people within the Gen Z generation struggle with is accepting failure if you send a message to a person on Linkedin and don’t receive a response. Go the next time knowing you gave it your best shot and I can promise you there are many individuals out there who love to network, and not only are they giving up their time to meet you, you are giving up your time to meet them, which they will be aware of. They will be aware that you are going out of your way to meet them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I missed anything out which you think is really vital to networking, don’t be afraid to let me know, but that is my take on networking as a young professional based in London, hopefully you can apply some of these yourself and you never know what might be a result of it. One small change in your career can possibly dictate how the rest of your working life may work out, the butterfly effect.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I Chose A Degree Apprenticeship Over University</title>
      <link>/post/degree-apprenticeship-over-uni/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/degree-apprenticeship-over-uni/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, I want to talk about why I chose the newest type of scheme, a degree apprenticeship, over the traditional university route. But before this, I want to address some of the negative connotations that are associated with apprenticeships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Occasionally, you find people who when they hear about apprenticeships, they think of traditional roles such as construction, hairdressing amongst others. Whilst these types of apprenticeships still remain, since the introduction of the apprenticeship levy and degree apprenticeships in recent years, there has been an increase in the number of apprentices in sectors such as the financial sector, technology and entertainment companies. Whilst earning a qualification, in some cases a degree, this scheme may well put them ahead of graduates who find it difficult to find a role due to high levels of competition for graduate roles. These opportunities exist in roles such as Data Science, Software Engineering, Digital Marketing, Finance and various other fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many companies upon the completion of an apprenticeship will retain their employees due to their working knowledge of the existing companies facilities. For example, within technology roles, graduates who have come from university tend to have little experience working on real-life projects with deadlines. Meaning, they are not used to programming for several hours at a time, and may not understand industry practices such as the agile methodology, where tasks are completed in a more structured way. I have found that many graduates struggle to understand concepts such as version control and have limited experience using Git, the industry-standard version control software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I do not want to discredit the traditional university route, as I still believe it is an extremely valuable way to get a job within a company, and there are still many fields for which apprenticeships are not being advertised. Many of the most career-focused individuals I have met prefer the theoretical knowledge university aims to provide, rather than the more applied learning of apprenticeships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being said, I believe that a degree apprenticeship was the right route for me as I have a rough idea of what career I want to pursue. I believe that the opportunity to work on some of the bank’s most interesting projects, combined with the theoretical knowledge provided by the degree I will eventually earn, will provide me with a more complete learning experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I highly encourage any aspiring data scientists/technologists to consider apprenticeships as well as university, even if you only have a rough idea of what career you wish to pursue. If you do not feel in the right frame of mind to make a decision, there is always the opportunity to take a year off to truly find your passion. Or, if you know that university aligns with your goals within the future, seize the opportunity with both hands and don&amp;rsquo;t look back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To summarise, I would consider an apprenticeship if you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have a rough idea of what you want to achieve in the future or if the career path you want to pursue offers an apprenticeship in the sector of work you want to pursue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you work in a creative role, generally a portfolio of work will showcase your work far more than any piece of paper could ever provide.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you want to gain real-life experience for a company where you will be at the forefront of change.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, university offers the chance to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn a more specific skill set, I was quite fortunate in gaining a place on one of the only Data Science degree apprenticeships, however, university offers a wider range of subjects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you want to enter a profession where university is required, such as Medicine or Law. However, even then, attitudes are starting to change.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have more free time, this is often overlooked however at university, you&amp;rsquo;ll have the freedom to pursue any idea you have without the constraints of a full-time job.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is my take on apprenticeships compared with university. I found that an apprenticeship aligned with my goals, and through it, I have gained invaluable experience. However, each person should follow your gut instinct as that is generally where you will be most fulfilled within your career. All the best in your journeys and if you need any support, feel free to reach out to me.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
